Guide to the Israel Heritage Room Committee Collection, 1929-2013 UA.40.13
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Israel Heritage Room Committee Collection
1929-2013
ULS Archives & Special Collections
University of Pittsburgh. Nationality Rooms Program. Israel Heritage Room Committee
UA.40.13
6.5 Linear Feet (11 boxes)
Dedicated in 1987, the Israel Heritage Room (IHR) was the 20th Nationality Classroom constructed in the Cathedral of Learning and the first to be built in thirty years. Its construction marked the revival and continuation of the Nationality Rooms project begun by Chancellor John Bowman in 1926. The collection comprises correspondence, construction reports, invoices, newsletters, research notes, promotional event flyers, timesheets, disbursement requests, financial records, interdepartmental memos, by-laws, design proposals, scholarship applications and reviews, newspaper and magazine publications, scripts, a video contract, and photographs. Digital reproductions of selected photographs are online.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Deposited by Nationality Rooms Program Office on October 30, 2013.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into the following six series:
Series I. Original Deposit (1991)
Series II. Israel Heritage Room Creation
Series III. Israel Heritage Room Administrative Records
Series IV. Publicity and Contributors
Series V. Other Multimedia
Series VI. Architectural Files
Separated Material
Architectural files are located in flat file storage (Map-case 30, Drawer 2, Folder 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6).
History
The construction of the Israel Heritage Room (IHR) marked the revival and continuation of the Nationality Rooms project. The IHR was the first room to be built in thirty years, the first to be housed on the third floor, and the first under the supervision of Nationality Rooms Director E. Maxine Bruhns. The twentieth classroom for the Cathedral of Learning, the IHR was in the planning stages for 21 years, and was on the mind of the Pittsburgh Jewish community since 1948 when Israel became a country and qualified by Nationality Rooms Program rules to join the Nationality Council and have their own classroom. Charles Rosenbloom, a prominent member of the Pittsburgh Jewish community and philanthropist, formed the Israel Heritage Room committee in Pittsburgh and its brother committee in Israel. After a hiatus due to the Israeli war with Egypt in 1967 and the Yom Kippur War in 1973, Rosenbloom was joined by Joseph Katz, the new chairman of the committee, and moved into the design, fundraising, and construction stage of the project.
Several years of design issues followed. After a handful of false starts, New York designer Alexander Kaufman was brought in to complete the room design with Martin Chetlin. A first century Israeli stone dwelling was chosen to highlight both the shared heritage of all Jews and the rabbinic tradition of learning and study which would lend itself well to a classroom. Artifacts and replications from that era were picked to decorate the space: a hand-cut stone floor, Capernaum stone bench seating, a lion mosaic, Dura Europos chalkboard panels, a hand carving of the ten commandments, jars, a Capernaum frieze, and a length of the Dead Sea Scrolls. The construction was completed in 1987 and dedicated on November 1st of that year.
The IHR, in accordance with the mission statement for the Nationality and Heritage Room Committees, promotes and represents its culture and traditions through events, performances, lectures, films, and exhibits. They also host scholarships for summer study in Israel for sophomore, junior, and graduate students from the University of Pittsburgh. The IHR is still an active committee and regularly meets to host and promote Jewish events and study abroad for the Pittsburgh community.
Custodial History
In accordance with preserving activities of each classroom on the Nationality Rooms Council, the Nationality Rooms Program office, located on the 12th floor of the Cathedral of Learning, was the original recipient of the Israel Heritage Room (IHR) material. The collection, including material later received, was transferred to the University Archives in fall 2013.
Existence and Location of Copies
Digital reproductions of the photographs from the collection are available online. Video and audio materials in the Israel Heritage Room Collection have copies located in the Nationality Rooms Program office. Videotapes were converted to DVD, cassette tapes were converted to CDs and the originals discarded.
Previous Citation
Israel Heritage Room Committee Collection, 1929-2013, UA.40.13, University Archives, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Scope and Content Notes
The Israel Heritage Room Committee Collection is composed of correspondence, construction reports, invoices, newsletters, research notes, promotional event flyers, timesheets, disbursement requests, financial records, interdepartmental memos, by-laws, design proposals, scholarship applications and reviews, newspaper and magazine publications, scripts, a video contract, photographs, DVDs, and a CD. The collection was originally housed and maintained by the Nationality Rooms Program Office, which handles outreach, promotion, and scholarship opportunities as well as administrative records management on behalf of the members of the Nationality Council.
The collection is arranged by series and subseries. There are six series in total. Series I comprises the first material deposited at the Nationality Rooms office. It richly documents the history, design, and fundraising of the IHR primarily from the 1960s to the 1980s. Series II is composed of records involved with the creation and maintenance of the IHR including: correspondence, construction and financial reports, maintenance memos, design research records and proposals, and disbursement requests from 1964-2009. Series III is composed of administrative records for the running of the Israel Heritage Room program. This includes: by-laws, membership and board member lists, promotional event flyers, newsletters, donations, minutes, in-house program planning, and dues from 1986-2013. Series IV contains publication and contributor information, this includes: event invitations, correspondence, obituaries, video scripts, a contract with AEG, event flyers, speech drafts, photographs, and newspaper and magazine articles from 1964-2013. Series V contains multimedia other than paper that were originally separated but relate to the Israel Heritage Room. This includes photographs, DVDs, and a CD from 1982-1997. Series VI contains architectural files of IHR designs, the bulk from 1982-1986.
Record reproduction was undertaken for newspaper articles, videotapes, DVDs, cassette tapes, and CDs. The newspaper articles were copied on acid-free paper and the originals destroyed. Videotapes were reformatted onto DVDs. All DVDs and CDs were copied twice: once for inclusion to this collection, and once for the Nationality Rooms Program office to retain. Cassette tapes were reformatted onto CDs and were also copied twice for the same reason as above.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Equipment in the Archives Service Center is required for DVD and CD playback.
Slides (Photographs); University of Pittsburgh; Classrooms -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Jews -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Universities and colleges -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Architectural drawings (Visual works); Clippings (Information artifacts); Correspondence; Financial records; Minutes (Administrative records); Photographs; Sound recordings; Video recordings (physical artifacts); Nationality Rooms (Cathedral of Learning, Pittsburgh, Pa.); University of Pittsburgh. Nationality Rooms Program. Israel Heritage Room Committee; Israel Heritage Classroom (Cathedral of Learning, Pittsburgh, Pa.); Pelzig, Perli; University of Pittsburgh. Nationality Rooms Council; University of Pittsburgh. Nationality Rooms Program; Cathedral of Learning (Pittsburgh, Pa.); Weiner, Margery; Toker, Franklin; Chetlin, Martin; Rosenbloom, Charles J.; Katz, Joseph M.; Kaufman, Alexander
- Original Deposit (1991), 1929-1990; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  This original deposit was initially inventoried and arranged in 1991. It contains the most substantive material documenting the history, design, and fundraising of the IHR during the 1960s-1980s.
  - History, 1.
    - Undated (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 2.
    - 1976-1987 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - 1972-1975 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - 1970-1971 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - 1929-1969 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Design and Concept, 1966-1986; 3.
    - 1966-1971 (Box 10, Folder 6)
      In oversize file 8.15.10: blueprints of 123-124.In oversize file 8.15.10: blueprints of 123-124.
    - 1972 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - 1973 (Box 10, Folder 8-9)
    - 1973-1978 (Box 10, Folder 10)
      In oversize file 8.15.10: blueprints.
    - 1979-1986 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Design—Toker, 1980-1983; 4.
    - 1980 (Box 10, Folder 12-13)
    - 1981 (Box 10, Folder 14)
    - 1982 (Box 10, Folder 15)
      In oversize file 8.15.10: furniture sketches.
    - 1983 (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - Design—Chetlin, 1982-1989; 5.
    - 1982-1983 (Box 10, Folder 19)
      In oversize file 8.15.10: Perli Pelzig IHC perspective.
    - 1983 (Box 10, Folder 20)
    - 1984 (Box 10, Folder 21)
    - Draft, June 1984 (Box 10, Folder 22)
    - 1984 (Box 10, Folder 23)
    - 1985 (Box 10, Folder 24-25)
    - 1986 (Box 10, Folder 26)
    - 1986-1987 (Box 10, Folder 27)
    - 1987 (Box 10, Folder 28)
      In oversize file 8.15.10: sketches of the door panels and window arches.
    - 1987-1989 (Box 10, Folder 29)
      In oversize file 8.15.10: sketches of the mosaic and frieze.
  - Fundraising, 1981-1989; 6.
    - 1981-1986 (Box 10, Folder 30)
    - 1986 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - 1987 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - 1987-1988 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - January 1989 and undated (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Donor Book, n.d.; 7.
    - Undated (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Construction Blueprints, n.d.; 8. (Box 11, Folder 36)
    - Undated (Box 11, Folder 6)
      In oversize file 8.15.10: floor plans and blueprints.
  - Construction Minutes, 1986-1987; 9.
    - 1986-1987 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - 1987 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Dedication, 1987; 10.
    - 1987 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Undated (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Furnishings, 1988-1990; 11.
    - 1988-1989 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - 1989-1990 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Publicity, n.d.; 12.
    - Undated (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Newsletter, n.d.; 13.
    - Undated (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Supporting Documents, 1970-1988; 14.
    This subseries contains obituaries, "Specifications for Israel Heritage Rooms 336-337" spiral-bound, historical reports, "Expressions of Jewish-American Life" spiral-bound curriculum guide and data file, program brochures, E. Maxine Bruhn's handwritten notes, and five envelopes of photographs (mostly undated). The photographs have been digitally copied and are also located here: URL.
    - Histories and other supporting documentation, 1970-1984 (Box 11, Folder 15)
    - Histories and other supporting documentation, 1986-1988 (Box 11, Folder 16)
    - Specifications, 1986 (Box 11, Folder 17)
    - The Ancient Synagogue of Beth Alpha by Eleazor Sukenik, 1932 (Box 11, Folder 18)
    - Experssions of Jewish American Life, 1980 (Box 11, Folder 19)
    - Daniel Kafri Catalog (Box 11, Folder 20)
    - Louis Kahn article, 1972 (Box 11, Folder 21)
    - Nationality Rooms Directors Notes (Box 11, Folder 53-54)
    - Photographs, n.d. (Box 11, Object 1-5)
- Israel Heritage Room Creation, 1971-2009; II.
  This series contains information about the proposal, planning, design, construction, expenses, and maintenance of the Israel Heritage Room.
  - Proposal, 1972-1988; 1.
    This subseries contains correspondence about the Women's Committee and their assistance, the building fund, and development. Also included are policy statements, pamphlets, progress reports, summaries of design, and a newsletter calling for members for the IHR.
    - 1972-1977 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1979 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1980-1982 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1984-1988 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Planning, 1971-1985; 2.
    This subseries contains sketches, concept reports and reviews, architectural graphics, Israel trip logs, and correspondence about the design committee and budget. Because of concern for provenance, some dates of the folders in this subseries are a bit mixed together from previous filing.
    - 1971-1980 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1979-1983 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1981 (Box 1, Folder 8-10)
    - 1980-1983 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - 1981-1983 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - 1983-1985 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Design, 1979-1990; 3.
    This subseries contains examples of Hebrew text, pictures of the IHR before construction, concept designs for furniture and inscriptions, design proposals, floor plans, correspondence, guidelines for development, design submissions, and research articles. Folder 1 contains a spiral-bound report titled: Program for The Israel Room of the University of Pittsburgh. Folder 2 contains a folder full of research. Folder 2 contains a foldered preliminary concept presentation. Folder 4 contains a binder about the design of the IHR. Because of concern for provenance, some dates for the folders in this series are out of order due to previous filing.
    - 1979-1996 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - 1981-1983 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - 1989-1990 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Construction, 1982-1992; 4.
    This subseries contains room book orders, invoices, reviews of construction, research, service requests, progress reports, and correspondence to Anatoly Lendel about his furniture designs and about suggestions and specifications. A Construction Account is included in this subseries which has already been previous assembled and maintained in a large binder. The Construction Account maintains funding, construction expenses, bond reports, finance reports, contract sheets, a contractor's application for payment, change order forms, invoices, disbursement requests, and memos. Because of concern for provenance, some dates for folders in this series are out of order due to previous filing.
    - 1982-1988 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - 1986-1991 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - 1989 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - 1990-1992 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Construction Account, 1987-1991 (Box 3, Folder 1-4)
      These materials used to be housed together in a binder titled: Construction Account.
  - Expenses, 1980-1996; 5.
    This subseries contains two groups of expense reports. The first three folders, general expenses, were loose-leaf and had to be arranged. The other folders were already filed in order and contain more specific groupings than the first three folders. The first group contains papers about construction costs, invoices, time sheets, disbursement requests, reports on state of endowments, and correspondence. The second group contains papers about expense reports, financial reports, disbursement request, cash reports for construction, invoices, completion certificates, and correspondence with hired persons. Because of concern for provenance, some dates in the second group overlap due to previous filing.
    - General Expenses, 1980-1996 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - General Expenses, 1988-1989 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - General Expenses, 1989-1996 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Expenses for Artwork, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Expenses for Office and Agency, 1987-1988 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Expenses for Office and Agency, 1988-1989 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Expenses and Financial Reports, 1986-1987 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Expenses for Construction, 1981-1990 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Expenses for Construction, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 9-10)
    - Expenses for Construction, 1988-1989 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Expenses for Construction, 1989-1990 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Maintenance, 1984-2009; 6.
    This subseries contains correspondence regarding IHR maintenance, invoices, and reports about photographs, cushions, books, and lights.
    - 1984-2009 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Israel Heritage Room Administrative Record, 1971-2013; III.
  This series contains administration records for the Israel Heritage Room (IHR) and the Israel Heritage Council (IHC). These records include subjects about by-laws, IHC membership, IHC meetings, creation of the Book of Donors, minutes, fundraising, donations, dues, awarded scholarships, and room events.
  - By-laws, 1991-2002; 1.
    - 1991-2002 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - 1988-2005, 2.
    This subseries contains membership lists, election of new board members, and correspondence.IHC Meetings,
    - Board and Members, 1988-2005 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - IHC Meetings, 1990-2009; 3.
    This subseries contains annual membership meeting flyers and other flyers, printing requests for flyers, featured speakers, executive committee information, and correspondence about meetings.
    - 1990-1996 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - 1997-2002 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - 2002-2009 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Book of Donors, 1987-1989; 4.
    This subseries contains book bindery information, leather samples, rough drafts, a cover design, invoices, and correspondence.
    - 1987-1989 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Minutes, 1971-2002; 5.
    - 1971-1988 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - 1988-1992 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - 1993-1994 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - 1995-2002 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Fundraising, 1981-2011; 6.
    This subseries contains newsletters, forms and flyers, cards, letters, and reports of artifact sales. The first folder was previously filed and exclusively contains information about the Children's Campaign for fundraising. This includes: flyers, letters, correspondence, curriculum reports, surveys, and bulletins.
    - 1981-1986 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - 2002-2003 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - 2003-2005 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - 2005-2011 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - The Children's Campaign, 1986-1987 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Donations, 1981-2013; 7.
    This subseries contains correspondence, checks and newspaper articles about donations.
    - 1981-1989 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - 1989-2013 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Dues, 1988-2005; 8.
    - 1988-1994 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - 1994-1996 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - 1996-1998 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - 2001-2005 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Scholarships, 1980-2013; 9.
    This subseries contains letters from scholarship winners, applications, newspaper articles about scholarships, photographs, reviews of trips, Codicil of Golomb, and correspondence about winners. The second folder of the subseries was previous filed and contains papers and a folder about the scholarship winners, therefore the content was not rearranged.
    - 1980-1988 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - 1984-1999 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - 1991-1996 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - 1996-1997 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - 1997 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - 1997-1999 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - 1999 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - 2002-2003 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - 2005-2013 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Room Events, 1987-2013; 10.
    This subseries contains papers about the Room Dedication, holiday decorating, community service tours, children's school programs, and anniversary events.
    - 1987 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - 1988-1989 (Box 8, Folder 2-3)
    - 1990-1995 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - 2005-2013 (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Publicity and Contributors, 1964-2013; IV.
  This series contains records about the publicity of the IHR and its major contributors. This includes mostly publication records, correspondence, newspaper articles, and speech drafts.
  - IHC Video, 1996-1998; 1.
    This subseries contains A&E contracts, invoices, newspaper articles about the IHC video, ordering forms, flyers and advertisements, the video script, a photo list, DVD packaging design, and correspondence.
    - 1996 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - 1996-1997 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - 1996-1998 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Publications, 1972-2013; 2.
    This subseries contains publications about the IHC. This includes magazine articles (the Hadassah Magazine, The B'nai B'rith IJM, and the Pitt Magazine), newspaper articles (the Jewish Chronicle, Pitt News, Destination Guide, Pittsburgh Post-Gazette, Details, and Excelsior), newsletters (the Nationality Rooms Newsletter, Executive Board News, Jewish Studies Newsletter, and Israel Heritage Room Newsletter), pamphlets, and correspondence. Articles range from news releases, promotion, notes to the editor, and photographs. Because of previous filing, some dates are mixed.
    - 1972-1985 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - 1970-1990 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - 1985-1988 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - 1990 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - 1989-1998 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - 1997-2000 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - 2001-2002 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - 2002-2007 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - 2008-2013 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Public Events, 1980-2013; 3.
    This subseries contains manuscripts about public events hosted by or related to the IHC. This includes: flyers promoting choir performances, lectures, book signings, holiday parties, botanical garden shows, Israel's 50th Anniversary, folk dancing, workshops, an Israel Consul visit, and the 44th International Cabaret Ball.
    - 1980-1997 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - 1998-2013 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Contributors, 1964-2012; 4.
    This subseries contains papers relating to important members and contributors to the IHC. This includes correspondence, newspaper articles, obituaries and condolences, speeches, other publications, wedding anniversary invitations, and photographs. Notable names include: Doris Binstock, the B'nai B'rith Women of Pittsburgh, Gertrude Caplan, Sorlee and Martin Chetlin, Marcella and Wilfred Finegold, Margie and Jerry Goldberg, Joseph Katz, Alexander Lowenthal, Eva Mars, Samuel McCullogh, Albert Raizman, and Margery Weiner.
    - 1964-1997 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - 1998-2012 (Box 9, Folder 7)
- Multimedia, 1982-1997; V.
  This series contains a variety of records, from photographs, DVDs, a CD, and Kodachrome slides.
  - Photographs, ca. 1980- ca. 2000; 1.
    Selected photographs within the collection were digitized and available online.
    - 1981-1995 (Box 9, Folder 8)
      Photographs #1-14
    - 1982-1995 (Box 9, Folder 9)
      Photographs #15-58
    - 1990-1998 (Box 9, Folder 10)
      Photographs #59-85
    - ca. 1980-1996 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      Photographs #86-139
    - ca. 1980-1987 (Box 3, Folder 6)
      Photographs #140-208
    - ca. 1980-ca. 2000 (Box 3, Folder 7)
      Photographs #209-259, including 7 negative
  - DVDs, 1987-1996; 2.
    These DVDs were copied in October 2013. One copy of each remains in the Nationality Rooms Program office, another copy is included in this collection. DVD 2 was reformatted from VHS.
    - "Seeking Ancient Roots", 1996 (Box 10, Disk 1)
    - "Israel Heritage Room Dedication", 1987 (Box 10, Disk 2)
    - "Interview with Martin Chetlin", 2009 (Box 10, Disk 3)
    - E. Maxine Bruhns Interview on the Israel Room, July 1991 (Box 10, Disk 4)
  - CD, 1994; 3.
    A CD was made in 1997 from the IHR audio tour recorded in 1994. The recording is in English and voiced by E. Maxine Bruhns. This copy was burned in October 2013. The original CD remains in the Nationality Rooms Program office.
    - "IHR Audio Tour", 1994 (Box 10, Disk 5)
  - Kodachrome Slides, circa 1990s; 4.
    This subseries contains two kodachrome slides of the completed IHR.
    - circa 1990s (Box 10, Folder 8)
- Architectural Files, 1980-1986; VI.
  This collection contains architectural files. These files are oversized and located separately from the rest of the collection in Map-case 30, Drawer 2, Folder 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.
  - Toker Designs, 1980 (Map-case 30-2, Folder 1)
  - Pelzig Designs, 1983 (Map-case 30-2, Folder 2)
  - Chetlin and Kaufman Designs, 1984 (Map-case 30-2, Folder 3)